hey everyone welcome to another
awakening from the meaning crisis
uh discord q a we've got john vervicky
back
for his bi-weekly q a with that with
us and uh yeah thanks john for being
here thanks brett uh
again sorry for uh not making it here
here last time but uh
uh the akira don could only meet on that
monday
and so uh i wanted to be there for the
release of
of the meaning wave so uh i hope
everybody was
uh uh okay with me not being here last a
couple weeks ago
oh not not a problem and i i watched
that and that was great and i think a
lot of people over here uh
went over and and saw it as well so yeah
that was a great event and
i hadn't heard of him before so it was
glad to
get to get to know akira
yeah i really like the song too i think
it's really uh
i just really enjoy listening to it so
we've got a lot of questions queued up
so let's get uh straight to them
let's start off with uh kira
can you hear me yep i can hear you cara
awesome um okay so the question i have
is
uh john you've talked about you know the
use of psychedelics
in an appropriate context within the
confines of a within the
structure of a wisdom tradition yeah now
that we've kind of been going through
quite a bit with the
ecology of practices where would you say
that
psychedelics fits in with that ecology
of practices and
what else would you recommend having in
place
for that yeah i mean that's a very good
question
and the i mean so i'm hesitant to answer
you
i answer you i will answer you i'm not
going to cop out my hesitancy is
it's a question that i think ultimately
needs quite a bit of empirical research
to give sort of sort of a definitive
confident answer to
so please take it under advisement that
what i'm offering to you is
uh sort of mostly speculative in the
somewhat pejorative sense of the word
speculative um so i mean i think that
people should have a significant
experience
and i don't know what that means in
terms of years but years
i would think in which they have uh
developed quite a few of
the practices that are directed
specifically towards
addressing self-deception so active
open-mindedness for example
aspects of mindfulness practice and also
practices that are designed to link
between a propositional and respectable
knowing
such as chanting alexio divina because
that's the important bridge that's going
to be needed
in order to make sense of the
psychedelic experience
and then i would uh
also hope that within well i would
recommend a stronger term
i would recommend that within that
period of let's say two to three years
um they have also uh become
i think this is the right verb owned uh
within a community
of co-minded and co-dedicated people by
co-minded i don't mean that everybody
shares
the same metaphysical doctrines per se
but that people
like we see in the sangha or here on the
discord server
are meeting in good faith and are
edifying and
um supporting and affording each other's
uh cultivation of wisdom
so i would then see uh
use of uh psychedelics
happening not uh but ever by sort of
isolated individuals
within a particularly uh
sacred ritualistic context so perhaps
it might be something it might be
something
that something like an initiation
ceremony
that moves people perhaps from you know
a novice stage to an aspirant
stage or something like that um i think
it should have the same
kind of setting
as things like baptism had i don't think
it should be
initially something that people just
sort of do regularly
uh perhaps after that it can be
something that is used by
as long as it seems to go well with that
person
uh then perhaps it could be something
that can be used
a little bit more frequently perhaps
like the eucharist was in christianity
uh so i think because it is a very
powerful tool
um it has to be that within
a a context that both
is cautious about its power but also
reverential about its potential for
supporting transformation in people
thank you that's helpful
thank you great adam you've got a
question yeah hey john
i had a philosophical question for you
what are the main tenets of for vacanism
yeah i don't know i didn't know there
was such a thing um
um meant the main tenets of verbatism
um
ah i
i don't know i i guess the the main
tennis ever
well i mean let's try in terms of sort
of traditional philosophical categories
since you posed it as a as a
philosophical question
i suppose the main metaphysical tenets
would be that your metaphysics
could try and get beyond both
uh a kantian and a platonic framework
uh by centering on intelligibility
uh um as the main uh thing that unites
your phenomenology and your epistemology
to your metaphysics
i think that the metaphys that your
epistemology should be
uh very oriented towards a phenomenology
and pragmatism
i i think it should then overlap with
um well i think something like a
cognitive science
to give us the deep interconnection
between our epistemology
and our particular our our scientific
practice that is relevant to both
uh epistemology and intelligibility
um and then all of that machinery what
used to be called
ethics but i don't mean ethics in the
modern sense i mean it very much the way
pierre
doe talks about it where we're talking
about the whole project of esthesis
the whole project of spiritual exercises
and the transformation of individuals
who are seeking wisdom should be the
core project
above and beyond uh other aspects
of what your philosophy should be doing
and helping you make moral decisions it
should be
centered on the sets of practices
that are most in concert with
your metaphysics your metaphysics of
intelligibility
your pragmatic and phenomenological
epistemology and your cognitive science
for the optimal transformation of
individuals
and uh collections of communities of
individuals like collections that was a
mistake
communities of individuals towards the
um cultivation of wisdom and perhaps
ultimately
something like an integration between
wisdom and
a systematic um and comprehensive
systemic transformation of individuals
that we might call enlightenment
did that answer your question uh
it did although can i ask a follow-up
sorry
yeah you you rang true on
intelligibility a few times and you
distinguished it from other philosophies
so could you play a little more on
intelligibility
yeah so i mean this is where for me
i mean intelligibility is i think
a a a nexus point you're thinking of it
like in a small world network
small world network of people's also
cognitive grammar intelligibility i
think is like
um the central hub because it links
uh aspects of your phenom aspects of
your phenomenological experience
aspects of your conceptualization of the
world
um and aspects of your theorization
theorizing about the world together they
they all presuppose
intelligibility and you can see that
there's ways in which
you're sort of you're into a couple
major choice points around this
one is you can go sort of the in the
modern route
in kant and argue uh following
occam that intelligibility is purely a
mental property
um it is something imposed by the mind
on the world
um or you can go the platonic view and
say that
in a sense intelligibility is completely
uh
uh sort of um where we want to put it
that intelligibility is
something that is completely
uh i don't want to i don't want to
attribute the wrong adjective here to
to plato so that intelligibility is in
some sense
i don't have a better but something
that's sort of a fairly abstractly
existing metaphysical entity
um and i think what the traditions
around
pragmatism and phenomenology have
brought out is
that that
intelligibility is some
property of things
real patterns of things that makes the
cognitive
act of understanding impossible for us
um and that although in
theoretical analysis we can separate the
cognitive act
of sense making uh from whatever those
real patterns
are in our experience they are because
they
mutually in our experience they
are interdependent uh and interdefining
for us
and so that's what the term
intelligibility means it means for me
the point at
that the point of if you'll allow me
because i talk about this a lot
in the series the the deepest point of
conformity
between the sense-making capacity of the
mind and the real patterns that are
found in the world
that's great thank you welcome
all right andre has a question uh that
he wants me to read can phenomenology
and cognitive science be implemented
correctly and fluently
together can heidegger's phenomenology
especially
ideas like equipment and being ready at
hand be applied to further
to those to cognitive science
is is that what the implication of the
last part of the question is
andre you're here did you want to
clarify
yeah well you covered a lot of it in
what you were just saying to um
adam there um yeah
so i was at a talk earlier today and
talked about um
some of your ideas i'm not sure what
lecture it's from because i haven't
watched them all i've only
watched one um but it was like an
oscillation between contemplation
and meditation and it was called
something ontology
and it there was an idea of um
using the attachment of um equipment
and when i saw the word equipment and
ontology i was thinking
in terms of hedger and things being
ready to handle uh yeah
present hand i'm wondering whether that
can work
so um yeah
there's a there's a
i don't want to be presumptuous sorry
pretentious a lot of my work is
actually built on work of what's called
4e cognitive science especially the work
of people like
bert dreyfus uh gallagher
people like like that and
these dreyfus in particular um
brought heidegger into cognitive science
in a profound way i agree with dreyfus
not everybody does
but i think a very good case can be made
that
uh a lot of heidegger's notions um
especially around dozen and the presence
of being and other things
in that constellation of ideas i'm not
equating them but they do form a
consolation
that a lot of what heidegger is talking
about can be understood in terms of
uh relevance realization dreyfus argues
this
specifically and it and it was precisely
because he brought this heideggerian
notion
into cognitive science that he was able
to challenge
uh standard computational models of mind
and introduce what has later been called
the frame problem which is exactly the
problem of how do we zero in on relevant
information from all the available
information i think that's very much um
one of the ways in which heidegger's
intersection with cognitive sciences had
a huge influence on my thinking
the work of gallagher and others
especially the people who are talking
about
um cognition as inherently embodied and
enacted and embedded
this of course is deeply influenced by
heidegger and even more so
by marla ponti and the phenomenal
phenomenology of perception so the
connections
uh there are deep or influential
they are very active right now and i
think they're even foundational for
what i think is going to be the dominant
model
it's already one of the most important i
think it will become the dominant model
of how you do cognitive science which is
called four e-cognitive science
third generation cognizance so um that's
why heidelgerian themes
uh recur throughout uh the series i have
uh
an episode dedicated to heidegger within
the series
okay thank you very much that that yeah
that um
cleared up a lot for me um and yeah
thanks for filling my questions
thank you i think it's a good question
and you know
the last few questions are brought to
mind you know the role that
these philosophers would play in in a
religion that's not a religion
you know in you know there are a lot of
people who
you know who who have read these
philosophers but a lot of people who
haven't
you know where do you see sort of
philosophical reading of these deep
thinkers as sort of required reading or
and would that limit its its appeal to
the general public who
may not be interested in in
reading you know these philosophers in
depth or have that capacity
um so no i don't see it as i
i i don't see it i don't think people
have to have read uh dionysus to be good
eastern orthodox christians or aquinas
to be good catholics
but i would also say that studying
a dionysus uh maximus or studying
uh a a augustan or aquinas will help to
make you
a catholic um so i think they shouldn't
be mandatory
but they should be held up as a
reverential exemplars
i was hoping to model
to exemplify perhaps is a better word
um there's there there there should be
individuals who
right this is gonna sound uh i don't i'm
not trying to set myself up but i was
trying to exemplify
that there should be people within the
religion that's not a religion who did
what i tried to do with awakening from
the meeting crisis and the other series
which is act and that's kind of you know
how i see paul vander clay and other
people acting it's the role
you know and this is dangerous because
we don't want to set up a priesthood or
anything like that
but there are people whose role it is to
provide
good mediation between
the profundities of a community and
the day-to-day life of people within
that community
so i don't think the role of i don't
think it's a mandatory
requirement and this is how it would
perhaps differ from
from other communities of the past i
mean
so i'm not trying to set up something
like plato's academy
um uh that's that's not what i think
is needed i'm hoping to participate in
what is already happening
which is and i i spoke on you know on
wednesday i spoke at the
the movement summit to all of these all
my
gosh i was overwhelmed by the number of
people
were there from all of these communities
of practices around a movement and
embodiment and mindfulness
they hadn't read all this philosophy but
i gave a talk about
how cognitive science and this
philosophical framework
can really help them to articulate
and access and enhance this practice and
build a community
and it was the reception i got at that
talk was overwhelming
so these people didn't feel like oh they
need to go out and read all this stuff
but if it's if it's done well and it
seemed to have been done well by
the response i get you know and what we
can do
is part with right we can i see that
there should be some people
uh this sounds so self-promotional but
that's the role i see myself in is
perhaps and i would hope there would be
other people would have that role
of doing that translation and making it
viable
and inspirational and edifying to people
who are trying bottom up to build the
religion that is not a religion
right thank you so andre
uh sorry barney you you have a question
and sorry uh
you got skipped over last week so thank
you for being so patient
for last month okay thank you uh brett
uh hi john um my question is
um how can i um
how can i make sense of covet 19 george
floyd
protest and climate collapse in a
metasense
so that i can put climate collapse back
on the
cognitive map or the attention map
because i feel it has been sidelined
with the
immediacy of covet 19 and george floyd
yeah so i mean
this is a really difficult i'm going to
be uh i'm going to hold off on sync too
much on this
uh but uh because jonathan pedro is
going to come on voices with raviki
we're going to talk about this um
but so i i i want
let me talk about it a little bit and
bernie i have to talk for quite a bit
a little bit uh self-referentially i
hope that's okay
um i sort of not commented on
this very directly not because you're
not making an important point
but i've been very concerned about any
bias that i might
care um what do i mean by that
there's aspects of this movement
that are difficult for me
i'm going to invoke an important
distinction here between that weber
makes between the manifest
and the latent function the manifest
function here let me give you a good
example of this
the manifest function is what any social
organization or movement a group of
people
uh makes us their explicit goal latent
function
is other functions it might be
performing uh that
are not acknowledged but are
nevertheless uh are
are causally important so a famous
example that
uh mark uh that favor not marx that uh
weber used
was bureaucracy um so bureaucracy of
course has the manifest goal of
coordination
coordinating behavior and making the
movement of information
uh very efficient it has the latent
function of allowing people
uh to displace blame and to discharge
blame and avoid individual
responsibility
kafka's high art because
literature is based on uh based on us
recognizing the tragedy
that can exist in the conflict between
the manifest and the latent
functions so i'm i'm i'm very
concerned about a lot of the manifest
goals
um that i i'm deeply sympathetic to them
i do i think
that the police have been overly
militarized since the patriot act
totally
um do i think that there are lots of
dirty tricks that are being played
against uh marginalized groups by you
know uh
voter suppression and and media
manipulation
totally and i think that's important
those are very important issues
i think it's a little too simplistic to
gather them under the term racism
but that is nevertheless an important
part of this
however so while while that manifests
part of it has
pretty much my unqualified support
blatant function is very very difficult
for me
because the latent function feels like
the fundamentalist christianity i grew
up in
that traumatized me i have people
telling me
that i'm guilty of an original sin that
i did not personally commit but that was
committed by my ancestors
and that there's nothing i can do about
it and any of my attempts to overcome it
are actually going to be undermined
by it because it's so pervasive and
profound in my psyche
and that the only proper thing i should
do is be endlessly contrite
and guilty until some external power
pronounces me acceptable for reasons
that i know not of
and so that that is very very
i've sort of recused myself because that
made me sort of angry and upset by the
demonstrations
not because of their goals which i i've
already said i think are there
are very important and laudable noble
goals
but what you might call the religious
aspects of these things
been very difficult for me to step away
from
and i think it's important
therefore to recognize that
there might be other people who are in
who are being attracted and
participating in these movements for
that latent function
of it has been going on and people have
been isolated they've been going through
domicide
they feel uh impotent they can't change
things
now what you have are gatherings
together
that are very ritualistic you have
iconoclasm the destroying of images
you have lots of stuff that um in any
other context an anthropologist would
say
a religious bit is religious behavior so
i think what's important therefore you
know and now i'm going to get back to
your question barney
i i i'm sorry that i took so long but i
wanted you to understand
why it's very difficult for me to speak
on this because i feel
that no matter what i say um i'm i'm i'm
not
i'm my my own bias is twisting things
i'm trying very hard
very careful about this i do think that
if that's the case and i'm
the reason i want to talk to jonathan is
he independently has made arguments
about the
religious aspects of all of the
demonstrations again independently from
the causes
that they are um directed towards
i think that if we can
remind bull that there is
that's what we're starting to do on this
discord service if we can remind people
that there is a properly religious
response to these
extinction threats i like what strawn
has suggested that
better than existential threats and i
like it i'm going to start using that
that there is a proper religious
response
to the extinction threats like like
ecological disaster
and i think we could potentially
address the latent function that has
made the topic
of these demonstrations so super salient
to people
i think the religion that's not religion
and what we're trying to do here is
exactly the right strategy
for answering that i think if this is if
people are honest
maybe they won't be i don't know about
this we can
say that there are other
issues that are as morally valuable as
important and important as dealing
with racism and and the consolation of
things around it
but also that can be can have a properly
religious response to it but i think
perhaps then a better response to the
degree to which
we more carefully and comprehensively
and in a confidently scientifically
rigorous manner
cultivate the religion that's not a
religion
is that at all helpful barney um
yeah let me just throw something real
quick here
um i've been working with faith groups
on climate collapse
and then when covet hit and george floyd
protest hit
they suddenly are besieged by white
guilt
and besties by the breakup of the
institution financially
and they're asking for orientation and
it
and my orientation is to provide
something that it can
further develop to also orient
themselves towards climate collapse
which is the
the heart of what i've been working on
so i was hoping
um uh so if another thing i want to
throw out is it could
one possibility plausibility is the
failure of
meta assimilation and meta accommodation
in past practices
that needs to be revived and i don't
know whether that is a good enough
of a good starting point
i think it is but i think the point
if people are so if they're already in a
religious framework maybe remind them
and maybe this goes towards what you're
just saying
about med assimilation and meta
accommodation guilt is
ultimately a frame breaking strategy
therefore it is necessary for insight
and transformation
the guilt alone is insufficient you also
need a frame making strategy
and that's where love that's where love
especially agapic love
is is supposed to take the lead and if
and i mean i mean one of the one of the
themes running through
especially it's i mean especially
prevalent in christianity
is but ultimately the love should be
more important to you than the guilt the
guilt is ultimately supposed to be the
frame breaking
that affords a new and more profound
kind of frame making
and maybe that's what you're talking
about when you're talking about uh
the the meta assimilation and they met
accommodation
and so i think the degree to which
people and the
community that's offering not only just
frame breaking strategies
frame making strategies and make them
scalable and attractive to other people
i think is that's a way of being viable
now
that's quite what you want i would say
for people who are staying within
their faith community i would remind
them that
there is this deep tradition and it's
it's a constant refrain
that both of these have to be held
together
guilt the concern i have is when guilt
and anger
especially when they come together in
outrage they become exclusive
um they are framed they are merely frame
breaking
and they tend to remove people from
rational reflection
uh because of the way they trigger very
primitive processing in the brain
so we could perhaps remind people and
wake them up to
there was always sort of a stereoscopic
strategy
uh within the religious traditions it
was not always or never was supposed to
be just guilt
it was also supposed to be about love
and that love was supposed to give
people a comprehensive way of making the
new frame that replaced
the frame that was broken in the frame
breaking
that's a little bit more helpful to you
yes yes thank you very much yes and
i was going to suggest that you know
covet 19 and george floyd protesters
just hang over
from this um from just the lack of
matter assimilation and accommodation
from the past
well i mean i think i think kobit really
exacerbated
um the meaning crisis and i was saying
at the very beginning we were going to
see
large-scale tsunami sort of mental
health issues and
people really trying to do everything
they can to ramp up meaning
i think that's part of what's going on i
also do think that there
are legitimate like i said i think the
manifest issues
need to be addressed i don't comment on
those uh because
um that's i that's not my rule um
but where i can comment is what i
what i think is the degree to which this
overlaps with
meaning crisis may actually make it
worse in some ways the thing that i'm
seeing now and it's only anecdotal
but as as the the high
um the demonstrations are starting to
wane people are getting a rebound effect
right and and so meaning crisis is now
striking them as even worse
than it was before all of this because
like that
now now what do they do now what do they
do
yep yep i agree thank you john i really
appreciate that was very helpful
i hope that people treat what i just
said charitably i
i mean i i'm very torn about this issue
for the reasons i've tried to describe
and that's why i was more
autobiographical
than i normally am because i wanted
people i want people to understand
that i i i don't i'm not i don't have a
simple
response to this i'm trying to work this
out
precisely because i think there's so
much uh like there's
it feel and i mean this in in the proper
sense it feels kafka s to me
this tension between the manifest and
the latent
okay one issue that uh strong
strong and i actually have been debating
a bit is
you know how to address these issues
between the left people on the left and
people in the right who don't want to
talk to each other
particularly i mean there's those on the
left who seem not
you know a lot a lot of people not
willing to discuss do you
my suggestion was you know a dialogue
type approach and finding those who are
willing to
to to talk and and sort of demonstrate
those
and you know to show that we can have
those conversations
oh i mean that's part of the logos i
mean
we've had i've had and i keep reminding
people is i see dialogos
um actually within a whole pedagogical
program
but so there'd be there'd be practices
that led
into it and you know and edward rush has
the
um the empathy circling and what he has
explicitly done
repeatedly is got people who are
hardline democrats and republicans
go through that practice and what it
does very reliably according to him
and i think he's being very honest um is
it moves people
from sort of bad faith adversarial into
good faith dialogue
in which people both sides get
rehumanized a commitment to the
possibility of a shared process
starts to come into the fore so i think
it's not just
an empty hypothesis i think we already
have some it's i get it it's it it's
it's sort of ethnographic and anecdotal
information but we do have empirical
evidence
that this is in fact an efficacious uh
uh possibility
i think it would be good if people on
the left and people on the right
sort of see that they might have a
complimentary relationship opponent
processing
i i think pete both sides could
acknowledge
what they're not not what they're
they're very good at saying what they
make salient
they need to do is maybe talk about what
they background
i think the right tends to background
the fact
human beings are are beset by fate that
we are small mortal creatures that can
be overwhelmed by
circumstances that we we need to take
that into account and we need to
um band together to help people when
they are overwhelmed by fate
i think the left and that's why the
right often falls into cruelty because
it forgets that i think
i think the left tends to forget that
nevertheless although human beings are
beset by fate and they are mortals
um they are responsible for virtue
they're responsible for the cultivation
of virtue
and and that human beings also need a
a an environment that challenges them
and demands that they cultivate
virtue in a reliable and systematic way
and that's why i think the left tends to
fall into
um self-righteousness as it's besetting
vice
what's interesting for me is how the
seminal sages like jesus or the buddha
always criticize these two together they
always criticize
cruelty and self-righteousness i think
that's important i've taken that as a
signal
um lesson about well maybe we need to
to sort of look at this in a much more
comprehensive
fashion um and that's where that's why i
try to be i try to avoid um
being specifically political i'm happy
when people
and i like i think zack stein for this
when people want to do what
he i think rightly calls metapolitical
discourse which is what we're doing
right now
when we try and talk about what are the
conditions of possibility
that would bring about efficacious
discourse and interaction
and afford good opponent processing
within widespread distributed cognition
excellent that's right on along with the
lied to my thinking
strewn you have a question thanks ryan
it's good to hear you i'm looking
forward to some of your questions i've
read all your recent emails so thank you
for that
uh well i'm glad you enjoyed them um
okay so
uh i just want to say something before
you again um
strawn is doing for those of you who
don't know him very much but
and he's often working behind the scenes
i get this um he's doing some of the
most interesting
i don't know what i i i mean this is a
compliment
like like in the sense of mozart he's
doing some of the most interesting
variations on some of the deepest
aspects of my work
that i've seen anywhere and i really
want to i really want to compliment him
on that
well i think you're in for a treat then
[Laughter]
he said ominously okay let's go okay
um you gave me a very nice description
of intelligibility as the bridge between
tea information and
information and osteoporosis physical
ontology with respect to the formal
cause
i couldn't help but notice that the
parallels of that bridge and the bridge
in the agent's arena relationship as
well as relevant realization
and transactivity were the same
with this framing your control of
intelligibility as the norm of norms is
not all that surprising
and i believe that it does a lot to
explain your endorsement of spinoza
specifically his views on the
neoplatonic ascent
and the notion that ethics is about
right relation to the ultimate principle
however as much as you like platinus's
vertical axis in terms of ontological
levels you acknowledge that he has
nothing
of nothing valuable to say about the
horizontal temporal app
my proposal is this intelligibility is
the norm of the vertical axis
but agape is the norm of the horizontal
axis
sorry i'm saying yeah because i i
prefer interrupting but i mean i think
this is one of the moves that is sort of
central
um in christianity what you're doing
right now but please i interrupted right
i was just making non-linguistic noises
of approval
okay yeah it cuts out so i couldn't
quite catch it sorry about that
anyway this would make intelligibility
something like the primary principle and
agape by contrast the ultimate principle
and yeah so that i just want to get you
are you with me
yeah i think so i i i yeah i think so in
so far
yeah yes um the primary principle
in that you have different ways in which
um being is coming to being so
uh the vertical with uh platinus is very
much ontological
um and non-temporal but the agape as you
said is
uh through time and it's it's in that
sense historically creative
um yeah and that's an element that is
missing from spinoza
i see where you're going with this the
the the issue that i have
is people see hegel as correcting that
error but i think hegel he really
diminishes the vertical dimension
and the aspect of personal
transformation that is still central in
spinoza gets lost in hegel
um so um yeah it would be to go
beyond spinoza and bring something back
but not go the way that hegel went with
it
am i am i sort of seeing what you're
seeing yeah can i can i go further
because i think this might speak to what
you just said
okay so i would also stipulate that the
bridge of intelligibility
extends between the poles of the
propositional and the perspectival
while the bridge of agape extends
between the poles of the participatory
in the procedural
if you grant the notion that the
vertical axis is static and the
horizontal axis is dynamic
then intelligibility speaks to the
ground of being and agape speaks to the
pinnacle of becoming
or to put it down sorry or to put it
another way
i propose to you that this brings true
structure and good function
into beautiful organizations it's really
good
i like it um the thing i'm worried about
wondering about though is
[Music]
so you said that agape is about the
participatory and the procedural
but and so
um
how do you get the the affect that is
part that is central to agape because
that's a very affect is a perspectival
thing right
um it's about modifying yourself i i
i don't know um can you can you speak a
bit more about epic then i could maybe
uh
translate it so my worry here is we're
speaking orthogonally
you may be speaking about this sort of
in terms of
a metaphysical mapping and i'm thinking
about it in terms of a causal
relationship between cognitive processes
so take that into consideration but my
my but what i'm saying is
so agape is obviously a motivational
state and
as i've repeatedly said of it's not an
emotion or a feeling
it's an existential mode but it's
affective it right
it it motivates you it arouses you it
directly shapes your salience
landscaping it affords sophism
um etc so um and i take
those to be uh properly perspectival
experiences those are
alterations of the way in which
consciousness
is getting an optimal grip on a
situation that's what
affect in general does right is it it it
reshapes your
salience landscape and help your optimal
gripping
yeah okay so is it possible that you
have a perspectival
um disposition towards affect but that
the affect is ultimately
uh it comes from the participatory
rather than the perspective is that
possible
uh it could be i mean it could be that
um the difficulty is and this isn't just
my work this is redfield and a bunch of
other people
they see that participatory is creating
affordances
and then the the perspectival
selects the ones that are effectively
salient or significant
and and so and so affect
is basically uh like i was proposing to
you is actually a translation between
participatory affordance um and
perspectival salience landscaping
yeah i'll need to think about that but
fortunately there's a recording so then
i'll go over it very very slowly and
google and whatnot and see what i come
up with sure so i mean
you might want to take a look at the
word of the work of
brunenberg and retveld um
r-i-e-t-v-e-l-d there's a one from
2014 it has dynamical systems in the
title i believe uh it's a lot about
optimal gripping and this kind of thing
okay great yeah so also sorry one more
thing also the recent work of mark
miller he and i are working together
he's trying to bridge between um
predictive processing models of
cognition
and and my work and he also thinks that
affect is
is exactly that kind of bridge um that's
a couple of recommendations
okay i'll try and check it out thanks
well thank you
i found that very uh very
thought-provoking
really tasty thank you yeah well i enjoy
coming up with things like that so
i'm glad you're happy thank you
all right we've got a couple questions
that are actually more suggestions for
uh uh for dial
the logos partners for you so jay davis
go ahead
mic check one two yep we can hear you
hi uh first off a note of gratitude
thank you for all the work that you've
done so far and continue to do john
i really appreciate it and the outcome
at least in this server is
more than exciting anyway moving forward
a suggestion
um our and first question to
contextualize are you aware of forest
landry
yes and gordon hall has
um i think tried to get forrest and i
into conversation for sort of
circumstantial reasons
it hasn't happened and then uh
jordan's been sort of out of the picture
for the last couple weeks for personal
reasons
right so i i do have the direct intent
to ask him to renew that project um
when uh when he and i talk again we're
supposed to talk this wednesday
okay perfect so i guess my visceral uh
sense is already attuned to something
that's already unfolding
excellent so um that's very good um
second point is uh the other day
we were in the server having the joy of
the
presence of uh guy seng stock and i
tried to
i tried to relay one of your uh
speculations let's say
in one of your recordings that that i am
not able to
give you the reference exactly but
basically to paraphrase you
you're wondering about how would a
circle
respond or react to a problem being
dropped into it
i don't know if you remember bringing up
that point so i tried to relay that i
don't know if i was successful
and then i actually suggested that guy
reach out to you
so that thread of uh contemplation could
move forward
so i just wanted to take the opportunity
to get on track with that
uh housekeeping so to speak um
we i mean guy and i are in constant
communication meeting
we're meeting every second tuesday on
peter stoa
and we're doing we're doing dialectic
india logos and it incorporates a lot of
this
also in conversation with taylor barrett
who uh
facilitated the circling group i'm in
and he's been running experiments where
he has circling and then he dropped the
topic in
he's writing a chapter uh in
contributing to the anthology
that christopher master pietro and i are
putting together um which is going to be
done this august called internet
we're getting all of these people
together and we're all writing and
talking about
all of this the dialectic deal logos all
of that
excellent excellent so in closing uh
just uh
terminology i'm just maybe giving a
offering a name for something that's
already ha already has another name
but and uh considering both practical
experiential
uh uh lived experience
and uh going through your material and
other people's material
trying to name the experience of what
arises through
dialogues or any other uh inter
subjective into interpersonal practice
of
open good faith dialogue generative
discourse
the word that came up for me was
stereologia as
an analogy to stereoscopy you know
you're able to see in 3d and depth
perception
through the overlap of of two single
eyes
so stereology so the
notion of knowledge or whatever
that arises out of two people meeting
and and creating that something that i
don't know how to describe
uh um dialogue what do you think about
that stereology
stereology in english but going back to
the
greek roots stereology would be a
coin for that something what do you
think about that
i think that's very cool um because we
actually talk about the phenomena that
emerges
as the weak term uh logos or the german
term geist
so logos of course is part of the word
that you're coining there
um so that is actually i i like that i
think that's cool
um talk to chris about that because
there's a sense in which that's right
um you get uh it's it's it's
it in fact people sometimes even
phenomenologically report
they feel like you not only have their
own perspective but they have
another person's perspective right
beside them
almost like stereoscopic vision um when
you when they're doing these practices
that's cool i i like that all right
thank you great thank you for the
feedback just a name it's not the names
it's the practice that matters
yeah but but but naming things well i
mean that's reasons why we have myths
and namings
in so many cultures naming things well
also affords
enhancing the practice correct so
there's my offer run with it throw it
out
mix it up whatever it feels like uh is
right
so just my offering thank you very much
all right uh david kinesis you've got a
suggestion as well
um yeah i'm john i'm wondering if you're
aware of uh a guy named machines and
young
yeah i have met him in person and we've
had
we've had a conversation uh
what uh lengthy conversation it was an
interesting experience for me
um i think an interesting experience for
him
that children of course claims to
be enlightened um and i took him had his
word
um there was no reason to to doubt that
but it was interesting because in the
conversation what
what what he was most interested in
was actually trying to get use
of of the language from cognitive
science
i could bring to bear to actually talk
about
aspects and dimensions of enlightenment
experience
so i thought i found the whole encounter
uh very interesting i found it actually
also encouraging
uh that a person who
again seems authentically to ha at least
what a buddhist interpretation and
a buddhist interpretation enlightenment
is finding so much resonance
with a lot of this emerging cognitive
science
i found that very encouraging yeah i
i would suggest a public dialogue
for both communities to um
uh to listen to um
i've learned from him meditation and i
think you would be a good
uh logos or dialogue partner with you
because of his not only his wide
experience in meditation and other
contemplative
traditions but also because of his
scientific background as well
yeah science consult our consultant and
so forth so
yeah i think that's a good proposal i
will reach out to him
he's very busy so but i will reach out
to him that's a good suggestion
yeah all right
mark you have a question
hello john hey mark good to hear from
you
ah always always good to have you here
uh helping us out
um i i'm trying to finish up a couple of
projects but uh the next project on my
list to sort of tackle in parallel with
a much larger and possibly impossible
project is
figuring out sort of how to divide up
your ecology of practices
and figuring out this whole integration
issue i know we've talked about this
before
um and then um it's sort of like well
how how would you divide up the ecology
of practices it strikes me as
you could do something like uh movement
versus
mental only versus uh things that are
are integrated into your daily life
right like
more on the mindfulness scale um or you
could do something around
say the four types of knowing um
which is not my favorite model anymore
for reasons that will become apparent
eventually
um and and so i'm just trying to figure
out what the
sort of the i guess the different
methods of dividing up the ecology of
practices might might look like
because i'd like to start to do that so
that people can sort of grasp on to and
figure out which ones
like if i'm doing these two i don't need
this one sort of a thing maybe
if that's even possible so i want your
thoughts on that if i could get them
yeah so my thoughts on that are going to
be incomplete
and unsatisfying um because i've
there's been proposals and i've wanted
to work with other people on this before
and i'm happy to undertake it
i'm trying to come up with such
a schematization um and
the the couple times i've tried it the
projects have sort of
um collapsed they they didn't
they didn't keep going um so
what i've been doing now uh to try and
give people guidance and you know this
from from the sang is i've been trying
to get sort of
people design principles about the you
know relationships of complementarity
and layering and linking um i
i take your point to be well said that
unless people need
something more categorical and how
they put together an ecology of
practices so
i am happy to uh
enter into this discussion with people
who are
doing it um and it might be that we want
to talk
and i people are doing it bottom up
then we can put hopefully i can bring
some good cog side of bear upon it
uh i'd like to you know i've had a
couple of these discussions
with rafe i'd like to do it more
um i'd like to talk to you remark and
what's going on in the sangha for people
i want to see especially i've held off
on doing this too much because
as you know we're about to start uh
western wisdom tradition and i wanted to
give people a deep
breath of that before i didn't want
their
uh their taxonomy to be based just on
the eastern traditions
um because i think it needs to be
genuinely capable of a global kind of
pluralism but what i can tell you is i
can't give you
uh other than like i said some of these
design principles
and um but i i would like
to get this project going explicitly and
i'd like to be a part of it i think
there's other people that should
definitely be included and like i said
rafe kelly
uh comes to mind uh now rape uh rafe is
very committed to his own particular
ecology
uh but that doesn't mean he couldn't be
a very valuable source for us
i'd like to talk to some of the other
people that are
trying to do this as well and see also
what's happening here
the discord server i don't have
don't think i'm in the position to offer
uh you know some sort of
um authoritative top-down taxonomy
i am interested in uh your your implied
critique that
the method of um
memorizing psychology in terms of the
four ways of knowing is probably not a
good method i tend to agree with you on
that
i don't think the four ways of knowing
should be ignored i think there's other
important aspects i do yeah um right so
the design questions there's design
questions then there's questions
of you know how does cognition work
questions
and there's questions about you know and
i mean this in
strong sense of the practicality of this
um because uh like
we want this to be very flexible and
scalable for people
um and so and we don't want it to be
we definitely want it to be pluralistic
and not homogeneous um
so guess i i'm basically saying what my
concerns are
what i think should go into it admitting
it's really
radically incomplete but i'm i do want
to
want to take this up as an important
project and so
people who have the relevant expertise
on this uh and i gave you are one
i think and i think rafe kelly is
definitely some we need to we need to
get this discussion going and we need to
get it going soon
and we need to get it going in depth
hey john it's tyler it's good to see you
um yeah this is fascinating someone
mentioned forest land you earlier i
just had a few really good conversations
with tim alan
recently and we're going to kim is
amazing i love ken
yeah yeah really a great conversational
partner and uh very
sensitive and um introspective and
insightful so i we're going to be doing
an event
that's working from some of the the
stuff coming out of forest landry with
the femoral groups
i think in the next five or six weeks so
i know you and i
should be having a conversation soon and
maybe
that's how that would end what time have
we settled on a time
uh i believe it's the 23rd did i respond
to that email
i think so let me check i'm sorry for
making everybody wait i just don't want
to miss this opportunity
i think we're on for the 23rd
yeah absolutely so the 23rd for sure and
and
yeah i think if we can discuss some of
some of your insights and some of your
work and how that may tie into
the ephemeral group study and how it
will allow for people
or afford people a chance to to
communicate
to articulate and like to develop some
sort of community toss perhaps
it'd be great let me in i want that's
great very much
awesome
this may be a good time uh there there's
a lot of
people here some people who i don't
think have been here before
uh to talk about the your the lessons in
your meditation class
are are quickly becoming i think an
essential corollary to your
awakening from the meeting crisis uh
what was the intent yeah maybe you can
just talk talk a little bit about
about that for to introduce it to people
who aren't who aren't aware
oh so the awakening from the meeting
crisis is
uh philosophical right in that sense
it's trying to
cognite scientific and then it's trying
to give um
a a historical and scientific
theoretical explanation
uh of the meeting crisis
it's historical and structural features
and then also propose what kinds of
cognitive and existential individual
and you know practices uh could
uh potentially address the issues in the
meeting crisis
what i did not do in awakening for the
was actually afford people the chance to
start to train practices
and to start to build an ecology of
practices and this is why the discussion
with mark
i think i mean all of the discussions
here have been very important
but the discussion that i had with mark
just now i think
is is the most pressing of that issue
that needs to
get under further discussion but what
happens on
what happens in the senga
is we meet every weekday morning at 9 30
and i'm teaching people
uh uh meditative practices
contemplative practices building
practices
um uh like i said practices that are
complementary relationships linking
practices like lectio divina and
chanting
or practices that integrate movement and
mindfulness
like uh the tai chi walking that i
taught today and so i'm i'm
directly teaching people uh um
practices that are relevant
to awakening from the meeting crisis um
i'm trying to exemplify them trying to
example i'm trying to afford
um a community i think a very good
community i'm very
community is wonderful in which
they can cultivate uh an ecology of
these practices
um and get feedback encouragement
um uh from other people so yeah i think
you're exactly right brad i think
that um that
i don't like the word practical because
it's become a word that means
it's it it it's slightly pejorative
um so i i i often say practicable
which is an ugly sounding word so it
won't get confused um
but i think the uh the morning classes
and then also the way they are taken up
by members of the discord server here
are are the practicable component
that is as important and as necessary
as the theoretical component that is
presented in awakening from the meaning
crisis
exactly and and like you said so so we
meet at 9 30 eastern
and actually a little bit before uh
every day and even on the days when you
don't do your class to to do the
movement practice uh before your class
and then we meditate with you
we also meet again at five eastern and
we go through it again so we're trying
to
you know do it a few times a day and for
those who miss it but also to
sort of expand you know sort of push
ourselves to do it for longer
and more often so i welcome everyone to
to join us and
check out the the schedule we're coming
up to the end of the hour we have i
think
three questions queued up are you are
you okay for a few more or
how are you but i want to i want to say
one more thing to what you just said
because in one of the one of the
arguments
i returned to several times in awakening
from the meeting crisis
is that you need to reclaim
um the claim
that there are many truths that are only
accessible to us
in transformation that there are truths
of transformation and that
for much of what it's even to be known
in order to properly awakened from the
meeting crisis
not be known without also undertaking
the important transformation
that is aligned up to
those things that need to be known and
so
i think it's a deeper issue
secondly i just wanted to point out one
more thing brad and then i'll i'll be
happy to take three more questions
which is uh well i want to also point
people to and
this discord server knows about this
this is with verveiki because
those dialogues and biological events
are supposed to in fact
form a mediating role between
theory of uh awakening from the meaning
crisis
and the community and ecology of
practices uh that are found
uh in in the morning sega i just wanted
to say those two things
thank you for giving me the opportunity
to do so
thank you tell me you had a question
are you there coming
hi can you hear me yes you know you know
sorry i i actually sort of forgot i put
in my put myself in the queue
hopefully this wasn't already discussed
but i actually just had a quick question
um do you have any recommendations if
i'm personally interested in the tai chi
and ki gong
i think that's how you say it that
you've been teaching
do you have like a recommendation of
what to sort of look for i know like in
these kinds of
uh practices there's a lot of variety
so i don't know if you have maybe if
there's in these days
uh like an online or a youtube channel
maybe you might recommend or something
just to
explore that whole area more without
getting sort of lost in maybe some of
the
the more uh maybe
fringy aspect of it uh
i mean i i have been looking at them and
there's
and there's kind of also legal reasons
around this so i haven't actually
recommended a particular
you know channel yet um i might do that
i got to talk to amar a bit more about
that
there are important principles to look
for so
be wary of people who are you know
tai chi and qigong that will allow you
to move objects with your mind or push
things over without touching them
or all that uh bullshit um
so that's a definite thing be wary of
the opposite end
people who want to reduce tai chi and
qigong
knowing how to punch and kick they've
removed all the mindfulness
they've removed all the aspiration
they've removed all the philosophia
so those are two extremes that you
should
avoid it's very good if you find
somebody who's teaching tai chi
and sees it within an ecology of
practices
uh it has been my experience that
individuals who learn about it
in that way um tend to get the good
out of tai chi where people who learn it
as a sole discipline
tend to become most fundamentalist
about uh tai chi in a way that i think
is ultimately detrimental
uh to the taoist spirit behind tai chi
try to find somebody whose focus is very
clearly
on the practice and on you and not on
themselves
uh you'll meet lots of people who are
charismatic leader and wants to
want to convince you of their
specialness
by how powerful or whatever
they are um find a teacher that provides
some
uh forum this is very important in the
virtual world
in which q a is a
like a a a reliable um event
within the teaching those are some quick
uh recommendations
to to look for
and speaking of tai chi one of our
members alexi is
actually going who's here right now he's
actually going to give
us a bit of a beginner uh tai chi class
tomorrow
at 4 30 before the the meditation so at
4 30 eastern so
everyone everybody come to that we're
trying we're trying this out so thank
you
thank you alexi that's strewn you had
another question
yeah yeah uh this one is about the
written our design document
because what you said last time about
the cognitive science thing
opened the can of worms with regards to
metaphysics and so
what i wanted to ask is what does
metaphysics mean to physically
what does metaphysics mean to what's the
to to physicalism like you said in your
email
yeah yeah i i just i i'm just asking i
couldn't quite hear you
um so
uh so it depends it depends uh
i uh let the time we're gonna talk about
the type of physicalism that i think is
defensible
which is non-reductive physicalism um
so i take metaphysics to be uh you know
the term was given to us by aristotle i
take it to be
some reflection that comes after the
physics and is beyond the physics
and is supposed to give us the ultimate
conditions
by which we can make sense of the
physics so
i think that metaphysics has always and
this is how i see it as
fundamentally different from the
supernatural
and one of the things i want to try to
challenge is the assimilation of the
metaphysical to the supernatural
that we've inherited from our christian
tradition
so i think the metaphysics has always
been um in a relationship of continuity
with physics properly so i don't think
there's any contradiction with a
physicalist having a metaphysics
insofar as a physicalist thinks that
there are
aspects of physical reality
that are presupposed by physics and
therefore cannot be
established by physics that they're they
are therefore
the proper venue uh for rational
discussion and reflection
and plausibility normativity as the only
means of
justifying and establishing those
presuppositions
for example i think every physicalist
this is only one example
every physicalist is committed to
causation
but there is no physicalist there's no
experiments or i should say
that's i use the wrong word there's no
physics experiment
that can establish causation because
every experiment by its very nature its
intelligibility structure
supposes causation that mean that
causation is just some arbitrary
anomalous notion
i think no i think what you can then do
is do what you do
even within analytic metaphysics is you
try
and explicate and justify this notion
and explain how and why it can have the
role
it has within your physics um
and i think therefore there is always
an important role but it's an important
and i think
irremovable mediating rule between
something like cognitive science
and your metaphysics via your philosophy
of science
because if the philosophy of science is
exactly that place
where you are trying to work out um the
ontology of
all of the entities and the
relationships between them
that are presupposed in all of science
not just
physics and that that is therefore
like the important mediator in any kind
of physicalism
your metaphysics so um that's
that's what i take metaphysics to be for
many of the people myself included
who consider themselves non-reductive uh
physicalist but
nevertheless i think that uh both the
philosophy of science
and then further uh the metaphysics that
um
is that emerges in response to that
philosophy of science
and acts as i think an important
constraint on it
um that's that's how they see that's how
they do and see the metaphysics
i mean the problem with the term of
course
and like and this is one of the the
issues i have about it as i've mentioned
i think it for historical reasons that
are not ultimately philosophically
justifiable
metaphysical for natural
and magical in the pejorative sense of
magic
have all been assimilated together in a
way that's uh very dangerous
um and and i i think when many people
invoke the term
both posit both with from a positive
regard
and from a negative regard in the
current culture they're using the term
in that way that i i reject
so that's kind of what i would say at
least
i don't think that's a complete answer
because of
the subtlety of your thinking that's how
i would start the conversation with you
around that topic
yeah well i i basically agree with
everything that you said there so and
i think that was incredibly useful on to
also uh directly right model
thank you very much oh well thank you
strong
all right and uh before our last
question jay david just wanted to make a
clarification
but he's not assuming sole credit
authorship on
stereo logia its inspiration and
uh was arise from discussions and
that are documented in in this server so
i'll take i'll take that in hand i'll
try to remember to give credit to the
discord server then
last question was david you had one more
question
yeah john i'm just curious about your
own
traditions you've studied with the the
the teachers and
the lineage of all the i guess major
um practices that you you do in teach so
meditation
qigong etc so the the meditation
and the uh tai chi chuan
chi kang uh and so the the pasta the
meta the tai chi
and some of the chi kung um they were
originally uh
a individuals called brock and june
brown and then
robert young and they were both students
of andy james and
uh he was student of rose lee this is
the the beijing
uh tradition of tai chi chuan um
but andy did a particular thing where he
brought in vapassna
and meta and then june especially
did this amazing thing uh where i i
found
she really got them to flow together
pretty well
all the neoplatonic stuff um that's
um i'm sorry that's much more uh sort of
reverse engineering
and me trying to draw from various
traditions uh
there isn't a proper community or
lineage or heritage
which is part of the meaning crisis in
the west of course
so there i'm relying on a lot of people
who are also similarly
are trying to engage in this
reconstructive reinvention process
and then um and what i'm trying to do is
it's my best philosophical historical
understanding use my experience
uh with already extend established
wisdom practices from
uh asiatic philosophies and then use my
cogside
to try and get the best possible
rational reconstruction this is exactly
what i'm trying to do right now
and many of you get to see it happening
in public in concert with many people
right i'm trying to reverse engineer and
reinvent your dialectic
so that's that's how that's that's sort
of how it's it all comes together for me
thank you well that was great thank you
so much
john and thank you so much everyone for
the the great questions
i've posted a link to uh the awakening
for the meaning crisis discord youtube
channel
in the event tech so please uh go to it
subscribe
this q a and all the other q a's uh
although i'm a little bit behind will be
up our uploaded there so please listen
and like
and i've also posted a link to the
calendar uh so
please subscribe to our google calendar
and it will show up at your own time so
you know
when all our events are going on uh this
is a growing community
we're here for you guys so if there are
events that you want to
want to see here you know let us know or
if there are events you want to run let
us know
uh you know we want to make this we want
everyone taking part in this community
so thanks again john this was fantastic
thank you i i always enjoy
uh i always enjoy coming here i'm also
very pleased
that you know that people like kira and
mark are here
i i as much as i possibly can i want to
encourage
the integration uh between the sangha
and the discord server
um i think that's really wonderful and
important for both communities
so thank you very much uh bret for
helping to facilitate
that encourage that and being sort of a
constant presence there
acting as a sort of living bridge so
thank you for that brett
thank you so so thanks everyone that's
that's it for tonight
we've got a lot of a lot of other events
uh this week so check the calendar
and we'll see you all next time have a
great night bye
everyone bye john bye
bye thank you thank you
thank you john